<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pelagius redivivus. Or Pelagius raked out of the ashes by Arminius and his schollers</title>
            <title>Parallelismus nov-antiqui erroris Pelagiarminiani. English</title>
            <author>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837673</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2011</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1450:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pelagius redivivus. Or Pelagius raked out of the ashes by Arminius and his schollers</title>
                  <title>Parallelismus nov-antiqui erroris Pelagiarminiani. English</title>
                  <author>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Mylbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Daniel Featley.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of "A parallel: of new-old Pelagiarminian error", a translation of: Parallelismus nov-antiqui erroris Pelagiarminiani.</note>
                  <note>Directed at Richard Montagu.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Four pages are paginated.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A parallell.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title has "racked".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Montagu, Richard, 1577-1641 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pelagianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Pelagius redivivus. OR PELAGIVS RAKED OVT OF THE ASHES BY ARMINIVS and his Schollers.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Milborne or Mylbourne, featuring a garb or wheatsheaf on a wreath (McKerrow 356)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Mylbourne.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here fell lately into my hands, a Latine Copy, of the enſuing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell drawne, (as I am giuen to vnderſtand) by two Engliſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, at the requeſt, and for the ſatisfaction of a forraigne Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of State. At the firſt view I laid it aſide, as an euidence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I conceiued the truthes aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, eſpecially in this Kingdome, had no preſent vſe. But afterwards reuiewing it more fully, and finding it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular and punctuall in this kinde: and that on the by, it gaue much light to the Diſquiſition of ſome points now in agitation. I thought fit to tranſlate it, for more publique vſe. For as <hi>Zanchius</hi> complaineth with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of the Lutheran <hi>Vbiquitaries,</hi> that he found them <hi>vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> euery where to vex and moleſt him: So it is to be feared, that the error of the <hi>Vniuerſaliſts</hi> is too <hi>vniuerſally</hi> diſpread. Many men haue too much free-will, and take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues too free liberty now a dayes to aduance and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine free will. I would to God more had the power of grace to contend for ſpeciall and ſauing grace, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to defend her Supremacie aboue corrupt Nature. The errors touching theſe points, of no leſſe conſequence then difference, are here briefly ſet in view in a two leafed
<pb facs="tcp:2011:3"/> Tablet, repreſenting on the one ſide the olde, and on the other the new Pelagianiſme varniſhed ouer with a faire gloſſe by the penſil of <hi>Arminius,</hi> and his Schollers. The occaſion of drawing this Tablet, as I finde in the Latine Preface, was this. <hi>Acacius Baron of Dona</hi> reſiding ſome moneths in <hi>England,</hi> to ſollicite the recouery of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> was often ſet vpon, and much laid at by a ſtranger there named <hi>Roergheſt,</hi> a man deepely engaged in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian</hi> party, who, though he could not draw him from the trueth to that ſide, yet caſt ſuch miſts of doubts before him, that his Lordſhip for better clearing, deſired the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of ſome Engliſh Diuines, verſed in controuerſie of this Nature. And opportunely meeting with two at once, after kinde and reſpectiue ſalutation, he demaunded of them why the Diuines of <hi>England</hi> ſo generally diſtaſted the doctrine broached by <hi>Arminius.</hi> Their anſwere was. That albeit thoſe <hi>tenets</hi> were plauſible to corrupt reaſon, and ſet out to the beſt aduantage, by the wit and Art of the patrons thereof, yet that the ſacred Scripture (to which Naturall reaſon muſt bow, and ſtrike ſayle) throughly ſearched, and impartially ſcanned, gaue no ſupport at all to this new modell of Gods counſels framed in mans brain, And that the prime Fathers of moſt eminent note in the Church aboue 1200. yeares agoe, at the firſt birth of thoſe miſhapen Brats, daſhed them againſt ſtones, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that by the ſame Orthodoxe ancient Church, the new reuiuers of thoſe errors at this day were then before hand condemned <hi>in lumbis parentum,</hi> in the loynes of their parents, the whole and halfe Pelagians. The Baron ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what affected with this anſwer, as it ſhould ſeeme, taking it indignly that <hi>Roergheſt</hi> ſhould offer thus to delude him with falſe ſhewes.</p>
            <p>What ſay you, quoth he? The Doctrine ſo much ſtrouen for, and ſo highly extolled by ſome, is it nothing but olde hereſie new furbiſhed ouer? <hi>Certè ſi Arminius Pelagium refodit, meritò vos Arminium defòditis.</hi> Verily if it be ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:2011:3"/> as you affirme, that <hi>Arminius</hi> diggeth <hi>Pelagius</hi> out of his graue, you haue all reaſon to bury <hi>Arminius</hi> deepe, that he riſe not againe. It was not long that this Honourable perſonage, was againe encountred by this ſollicitor <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ergheſt,</hi> and further vrged vpon his former motiues. Whereupon the Baron acquainted him with the Engliſh Diuines anſwer, which like ſtrong Phyſick wrought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with his queaſie ſtomack, and brought forth from him the Catalogue enſuing, with a challenge, <hi>Quid tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Arminio cum Pelagio?</hi> What kindred or neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood hath <hi>Arminius</hi> with <hi>Pelagius,</hi> or with the Demipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians? This Catalogue being then ſent from him, and receiued by thoſe two Diuines, they iudged not complete enough to ſet out the bounds of the queſtion; but thought needfull thereunto to take in more ground out of the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger fields of thoſe Fathers that entred into the liſts of this combat. Accordingly partly out of that Catalogue, and partly out of the auncient Fathers, they make vp a kinde of liſt of the olde errors: and as for the new, they take them out of the Treatiſes of ſome principall Belgique Writers of that ſide: which, collected into a ſmall map, they exhibite to the Baron to be deliuered to the confident chalenger. Who vpon the receipt thereof, vndertooke to returne forthwith a direct and punctuall anſwer. But this Dutch Champion quitting the field, tooke Sea, and returned into <hi>Holland,</hi> caſting his promiſe to the ſame windes, that filled his ſayles. So is his <hi>forthwith</hi> drawne forth now diuers yeares, and his anſwer in vaine expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <p>So deuine and admirable is the courſe of grace, that it reacheth an helping hand euen to thoſe who through error ioyne hands and pennes againſt it, and enlightens the vnderſtandings euen of thoſe that caſt myſts to dimme the light thereof. There may therefore bee hope, that as <hi>Pighius</hi> endeuouring to euert <hi>Caluins</hi> writings in point of Iuſtification, was in that point conuerted himſelfe by
<pb facs="tcp:2011:4"/> them: ſo this <hi>Challenger</hi> conſidering of this anſwer, though with intent to refute the ſame, was himſelfe confuted by it, and rectified in his iudgement. For in this mirror of both groſſe and refined <hi>Pelagianiſme,</hi> any man that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not through a Ieſuites ſpectacle, may (though in ſmall modell) behold the true ſhape and temper of <hi>Pelagius</hi> his frenzie in <hi>Arminius</hi> his fancie, and reſolue, as St. <hi>Ierome</hi> did, in a like caſe, <hi>Aut Plato Philonizat, aut Philo Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizat,</hi> Either the Pelagian predeſtination was <hi>ex praeniſa fide Arminij,</hi> out of the foreſeene faith of <hi>Arminius,</hi> or <hi>Arminius</hi> his deuiſe out of the fore-read faith of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any, after hee hath viewed this table, caſt a ſcorne vpon it, as compoſed by ſome gloating Puritane, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne <hi>Criminis inauditi,</hi> of a new found crime, namely of doctrinall Puritaniſme all thoſe that giue any credit to ſuch <hi>Parallells,</hi> or differ from him in thoſe points, I will giue no ſentence againſt him, but referre him to reade it in <hi>Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. de Orat.</note> 
               <hi>Aut eſt ex ijs, qui illos non norunt, aut ex ijs, qui iudicare non poſſunt,</hi> Either hee knoweth not the parties whoſe <hi>tenets</hi> are here ſet one by the other, or hee wants iudgement to compare, &amp; for defect thereof, Coſens him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with Mountebanke wares. The prouerb is, <hi>Jnter caecos luſcum regnare poſſe,</hi> That among blinde men, a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blinde or blinkard may dominere, and put trickes vpon them. But, God forbid, that any of the <hi>Seers of Iſrael</hi> ſhould miſtake old hereſie new coyned, for current truth. At the firſt ſetting of the Mint on work by <hi>Iames Harman</hi> at <hi>Leyden,</hi> when a peece new ſtamped was tranſported, and preſented to King <hi>JAMES,</hi> our late Soueraigne, of moſt bleſſed memory, vpon the very firſt caſt of his eye, he diſcouered it to be no better then an halfe faced groat of the Semipelagian alloy. <hi>Et ſtatim perfodit ſtylo Regio,</hi> and forthwith ſtabbed it through with his Royall pen, and branded the Maſter of the Mint with the title of <hi>the enemie of God.</hi> And that the ſame iudicious King perſiſted
<pb facs="tcp:2011:4"/> in this his Iudgement, both of the Co ne and Coyners euen to the end, to mee it is a thing moſt euident, by a faithfull and allowed relation, which I haue ſeene of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers remarkable directions and inſtructions giuen by his Maieſty to two Diuines, about a moneth before his death, queſtioned before him about a booke then publiſhed, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Doctrine of St. <hi>Auſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that diſcourſe, his Maieſtie hauing occaſion to touch vpon the Treatiſes of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that are extant in the ſeuenth Tome, (which hee might ſeeme prophetically to recommend as a ſoueraine antidote againſt an euill vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeping ſince his death) hee ſtiled them <hi>St. Auſtins Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall tracts againſt the heretickes that agree with our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians:</hi> and preſently calling to minde their proper name, termed thoſe hereticks (from the Author of that Sect) <hi>the Pelagians.</hi> Which Paraphraſe of his Maieſtie, becauſe it giueth much life to the enſuing Tablet, and this Tablet light to his Maieſties ſpeech, I haue made bold to borrow the Character of the Preſſe, to imprint both more deepely in thy memory: and to expreſſe to thee my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſerue as a voluntary, (as did that excellently lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and zealous Archbiſhop <hi>Bradwardin) In cauſa Dei contra Pelagianos,</hi> in Gods cauſe and quarrell againſt the Pelagians.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="doctrine">
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2011:5"/>
            <head>A CATALOGVE OF THE PELAGIAN DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, condemned by Ancient <hi>Fathers, and Councells.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 THe ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> is not imputed to his poſteritie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Adam</hi> by his ſinne endamaged onely himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, but his Poſteritie onely by his example, ſo farre forth as they imitate him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is no Originall ſinne, or corruption of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Euery man is borne in the ſame perfection wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was before his fall, ſaue onely the perfection of age, which in his poſteritie wants the vſe of reaſon, when they are new borne.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Temperall death is from the neceſſitie of nature, and did not come vpon all the poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> for the firſt ſinne of their firſt Parent.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Adam</hi> himſelfe ſhould have dyed by the neceſſitie of nature, though he had not ſinned.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Much leſſe did <hi>Adam</hi> bring vpon his Poſtritie the guilt of eternall death for his ſinne.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Children in Baptiſme doe not receiue remiſsion of Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2011:6"/>
            <p n="9">9 Thoſe who maintaine the Doctrine of Originall ſinne, condemne Marriage.</p>
            <p n="10">10 By Grace is meant Nature endued with Reaſon and Will.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Supernaturall grace conſiſteth in the Doctrine of the Law, and pardon of ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Forgiueneſſe is not neceſſary for all. Becauſe all do not ſin: or at leaſt, ſome may be without ſinne.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Thoſe, who haue ſinned, may by the power of nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, without inward grace from the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="14">14 The grace of Chriſt is not elſewhere to be ſought for, then in the Doctrine, and life, or example of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="15">15 If there bee any inward helpe receiued from the Holy Ghoſt, the ſame conſiſteth onely in the enlightening of the vnderſtanding. But as for the Will, that needes no inward grace.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Man by his naturall inbred faculties is able perfectly to fulfill the Law.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Grace is profitable for the fulfilling of the Law, but not neceſſary thereto.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Man of himſelfe is able to reſiſt the ſtrongeſt temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: though indeed, he doth it with more facilitie, if he be helped by grace.</p>
            <p n="19">19 By the workes of nature man promeriteth (or gayneth) the ayde of grace.</p>
            <p n="20">20 That which proceedeth from forgetfulneſſe, or ignorance, hath not in it the property of ſinne.</p>
            <p n="21">21 In the New Teſtament all kinde of oathes are forbidden.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Rich men, vnleſſe they ſell their goods, and giue them to the poore cannot be ſaued.</p>
            <p n="23">23 The well vſing of free will, and of naturall powers is the cauſe of Predeſtination.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Chriſt dyed not for all men: at leaſt not for Infants; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are without ſinne.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2011:6"/>
               <head>The Errors of the <hi>Semipelagians</hi> or <hi>Maſsilians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 THe beginning of Faith, and the deſire of conuerſion is from our ſelues, the increaſe is from grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Man, if not alwayes, yet ſometimes preuents God, by the preparation of his owne will. By which endeauour of nature God is moued to bring, through the ayde of his Spirit, to the grace of regeneration the Will ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For perſeuerance in Faith and Grace there is no neede of new and ſpeciall grace. What we haue by nature, or haue formerly gotten by the ſpirit of grace, ſufficeth for ſuch perſeuerance.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2011:7"/>
            <head>April. 1. 1621. <hi>In the name of God, and to the praiſe of the glory of his grace.</hi> Epheſ. 1.6. A briefe anſwer, by way of <hi>Parallele,</hi> to the foregoing Catalogue, and to the Demand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſent; <hi>What affinity is there betweene</hi> PELAGIANS, <hi>or</hi> DEMIPELAGIANS <hi>on the one ſide, and the</hi> ARMINIANS <hi>one the other.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Index</hi> of the Pelagian aſſertions, conſiſting of 24. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, had neede of an <hi>Index expurgatorius,</hi> a purging Index, The laſt of them is no Doctrine held by <hi>Pelagius,</hi> but an abſurditie, or inconuenience, inferred vpon his <hi>Tenets</hi> by ſome; yet by him conſtantly denied in direct termes. Which this ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer might haue learned of <hi>Gerard Voſsius, Hiſtor. Pelag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>por.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. from whom he tooke vpon truſt this Catalogue. Moreouer to what ende is here raked together the draffe of ſo many hereſies, whereof the greater part was renounced by the Father, that begat them? As appeareth in many places of St. <hi>Austens</hi> Treatiſes againſt his hereſies. Laſtly, how imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent are thoſe propoſions concerning oathes, rich mens goods, and the mortalitie of <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency, &amp;c? Who euer, ſo much as by dreame, did thinke to faſten this vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Aminians?</hi> So that of the 24. <hi>Pelagian</hi> Poſitions here reherſed, ſixe onely may looke this way; namely, the third, ſeuenth, tenth, fifteenth, nineteenth, three and twentieth. The reſt needed not to haue beene preſſed for this ſeruice.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2011:7"/>
                  <head>1. Of Originall Sinne.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Pelagians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PPropoſ.</hi> 3. There is no O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall ſinne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Aug. de Nuptijs.</hi> Man is not borne with originall ſinne. Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſin is no ſinne: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not voluntary.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Adam</hi> did not bring vpon his Poſteritie the guilt of eternall death for his ſinne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of the Epiſtle of Gelaſius.</hi> It ſeemes not iuſt, that Gods creature, without any action of his owne, ſhould bee borne guilty of ſinne, or intangled in ſinne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item ibid.</hi> That children dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without baptiſme cannot be damned for Originall ſinne onely.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Arminians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARnoldus Coruinus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tilenus, pag. 388.</hi> Arminius teacheth, that Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne hath not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne, or fault, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arminius himſelfe, to the 9. queſtion, pag. 174.</hi> It is wrongfully ſaid, that Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne maketh a man guilty of Death.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnold. Ibidem pag. 391.</hi> Arminius indeed holdeth, that no man is damned for onely Originall ſinne.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Note alſo, that both theſe endeauour to ſtrengthen this their opinion with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments concluding not onely that none are actually damned for Originall ſinne, but alſo that none iuſtly can be. For if ſo, then</p>
                  <p n="1">1 God ſhould deale more rigorouſly with ſuch men, then he doth with the Deuills.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That which is a puniſhment of ſinne, cannot deſerue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhment. For then would there be endleſſe proceſſe, if one puniſhment ſhould ſtill deſerue another.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2011:8"/>
                  <head>2 Of the meaning of the word Grace.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Pelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRopoſ.</hi> 10. By the word Grace is meant, nature endued with reaſon and will.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 105. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius by that Grace which he acknowledged to be giuen without any foregoing merits, did meane the nature of man, wherein wee are created. Foraſmuch, as before we had any being, we could not merit that wee ſhould haue a being.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARnoldus Ibid. pag. 158.</hi> The Gentiles by nature do the things of the Law. And how little ſoeuer that bee, which a man in the eſtate of Corruption can doe, God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that he ſhould do it, and when man doth this, hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth grace well.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item pag 157.</hi> Vpon demand whether a man in the eſtate of corruption can rightly vſe the light of reaſon: he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reſolueth, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that a man in the eſtate of Corruption doe rightly vſe that grace, which he hath, and performe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he can, by that Grace giuen him.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>It need not ſeeme ſtrange that the <hi>Arminians</hi> make <hi>Nature</hi> to be <hi>Grace,</hi> who maintaine that there is a generall grace imprinted in all men without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which what can it bee elſe but Nature, and her endowments? Now if any ſhall obiect, that this in effect is nothing but an idle ſtrife about wordes, let him conſider, that this is the hidden ſpring of the moſt peſtilent poyſon of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> For out of this
<pb facs="tcp:2011:8"/> may they waſh away and put off any thing, that is brought by the maintainers of <hi>Grace.</hi> If alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be made againſt them, that <hi>We are ſaued by grace.</hi> Their anſwere is ready. True. To witt by nature, which is the firſt and generall grace. <hi>By grace I am that I am.</hi> True. By grace, that is by nature, whereof God is the free Donor. <hi>Faith is the gift of God.</hi> True. Becauſe our free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, by which we aſſent, is the gift of God the Creator. And if St. <hi>Auſten</hi> himſelfe ſhall preſſe againſt them, that <hi>Grace onely diſcernes a beleeuer from an vnbeleeuer.</hi> Why may they not anſwere. True ſir. That is, onely Free-will, which is moſt freely giuen vs by God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>3 Of the cauſe of the increaſe of Grace.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Pelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRopoſ.</hi> 19. By the works of nature a man promeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, or gaineth the aide of grace.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell at Dioſpolis.</hi> Grace is giuen according to mens merits.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Saint Auſten in his Treatiſe of Perſeuerance.</hi> Three points there are which the Catholique Church doth principally maintaine againſt the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2011:9"/> Whereof the firſt is, that <hi>Grace</hi> is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen according to our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſame Aug.</hi> Grace (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Pelagius</hi>) is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen though not according to the deſert of good workes, yet according to the deſert of a good will. His reaſon is: Otherwiſe God ſhould be an accepter of perſons, if hee ſhould haue mercy on whom hee will, without any fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going merits.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARminius Exam. pag. 218.</hi> Tell me Sir, in this ſpeach of Chriſt, To him that hath ſhall be giuen, Is not that promiſe conteined, by which God engageth himſelfe to enlighten with ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall grace him, who well v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the light of nature, or at leaſt vſeth it leſſe ill?</item>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2011:9"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnoldus againſt Tilen, pag. 165.</hi> The cauſe why the Goſpell is reuealed to babes, is becauſe they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ready to learne. The rule is generall, which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without limitation that, To him that hath, that is, well vſeth, God will giue grace.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>4 Of the ayde of Grace in conuerſion.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Pelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRopoſit.</hi> 15. If there bee any inward helpe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the holy Ghoſt, that conſiſteth onely in the enlightening of the vnderſtanding. But as for the Will, that needes no inward Grace.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2011:9"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Saint Aug. ad Bonif.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. We receiue from the Lord the helpe of knowledge, whereby we know thoſe things which ought to be done, but not the inſpiration of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that wee may with an holy loue performe thoſe things we know, which is properly Grace.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe Hage Conference ſet out by Bertius, pag. 279.</hi> Infuſion of holyneſſe hath no place in the will. In aſmuch as the Will in its owne nature is free to will good or euill.— In the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall death, the gifts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called ſpirituall, are
<pb facs="tcp:2011:9"/> ſeparated from the will of man, becauſe they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in it; but onely a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of doing well, or ill.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibidem, pag. 272.</hi> God will giue a new heart. We thinke that by <hi>heart</hi> is meant the ſoule of man; and that it is called new; both in regard of the infuſion of newe light and knowledge, and alſo in reſpect of new workes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, which it ſelfe bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>5 Of the cauſe of Predeſtination.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Pelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRopoſ.</hi> 23. The well vſing of Free well, and naturall powers is the cauſe of Praedeſtination.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>The <hi>Arminians</hi> doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but that the decree of Gods Election dependeth vpon the foreſeene free aſſent of mans will, euen then when all the helps of ſauing grace being afforded, it may yet diſſent by its owne naturall and inbred liberty: as hereafter appeareth. Why therefore may they not climbe to the very top of Pelagianiſme, and ſo auow, that the good vſe of our natural freewill doth poiſe downe the euen balance of Gods Praedeſtination, and determine the otherwiſe wauering decree of God? Howſoeuer they decline the name of <hi>Cauſe</hi> in election, and hold forth in ſtead thereof the attribute of a <hi>foregoing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet in effect they muſt needs hit againſt this rocke, at which <hi>Pelagins</hi> ſuffered Shipwracke.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2011:10"/>
               <head>As for <hi>Demipelagianiſme,</hi> there are but three heads of that <hi>Hydra</hi> put foorth in this Catalogue; <hi>the other lye hidden, and pulled in, like the hornes of a</hi> Snaile being touched. Which here (by the helpe and hand of the moſt ſound Fathers) are to be drawn forth, and to be clapt on the <hi>ſhoulders of thoſe, who in theſe times act the ſame parts.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>1 Of Election vpon foreſeene Faith.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelagians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>OVt of Saint Proſpers Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to Saint Auſten.</hi> That God foreknew before the foundation of the world, Who would beleeue, and perſeuere in that faith, which in proceſſe ſhould be helped by grace. And that hee Praedeſtinated thoſe to his Kingdome, whom, being freely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, hee foreſawe would become worthy of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and depart this life making a good end.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2011:10"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of the Epistle of Saint Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary to Saint Auſten extant in the ſeuenth Tome of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens Workes.</hi> They (the <hi>Demipelagians</hi> or <hi>Maſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi>) will haue Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination to reach no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then this, that God Praedeſtinated, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knew, or decreed to elect thoſe that would beleeue.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Arminians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>HAge Conference, pag. 62. Bert.</hi> God before the Foundations of the World were layed appointed to ſaue by Chriſt, thoſe out of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, who by the grace of the ſpirit would beleeue, and perſeuere in that faith and obedience by the ſame grace.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item. Ibid.</hi> The purpoſe to ſaue thoſe, that perſeuere in faith, is the whole entire decree of Election.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item pag. 90.</hi> That preciſe and and abſolute decree, whereby God is ſaid in Electing to
<pb facs="tcp:2011:10"/> conſider theſe, or thoſe men, no otherwiſe then as ſingular perſons, and to haue had no reſpect vnto the good quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which he foreſawe— ſuch a Decree cannot ſtand with the nature of God, or with the Scriptures.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arminius againſt Perkins, pag. 221.</hi> I deny that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is the rule of giuing or not giuing Faith.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hage Confer. pag. 38.</hi> Wee profeſſe openly, that Faith in Gods foreſight and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is before Election to ſaluation, and doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Election, as a fruit thereof.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>2 Of the vncertaine number of the Elect.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelagians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRoſpers Epiſtle to Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten.</hi> They would not yeeld that the number of the Praedeſtinated cannot bee encreaſed or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2011:11"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hilar. Arelatenſ. to Saint Auſten.</hi> Likewiſe they will not admit the number to be certaine of thoſe, that are to be elected, and thoſe that are to be reiected.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> That there are not of men ſome deputed to life, others to deſtruction, but that men may paſſe from ſaluation to perdition, and from perdition to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Arminians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>GRevinchov. in his The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes exhibited, pag. 137- and others.</hi> Vncomplete E, lection may bee interrupted, and ſometime is. And thoſe, that are vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pletely elected.
<pb facs="tcp:2011:11"/> are truely Elect. Yet may they become Reprobates, and periſh. And the number of the Elect may bee encreaſed and diminiſhed.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item.</hi> No man as long as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in this life, is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily elected: But hee onely is peremptorily elected, who dyeth, or rather is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready dead, in faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>(So by this reckoning no man liuing is an Elect)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>3. Of the vniuerſalitie of Grace and calling.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>OVt of Proſpers Epiſtle to Saint Auguſtine, extant in Saint Auſtens ſeuenth Tome.</hi> They ſay, that all men vniuerſally are called to ſaluation either by the Law of Nature, or the written Lawe, or by the preaching of the Goſpell.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARnold againſt Tilen. pag. 397.</hi> God by his Spirit, effectuall in the Law, worketh after ſome manner, and in ſome degree in all men; to the ende, that by little and little they may bee brought to the faith of Chriſt, whom God for his part is ready to reueale to all men.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2011:11"/>
                  <head>4 Of workes of Praeparation.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THe firſt Propoſition.</hi> The beginning of Faith and deſire of Conuerſion is from our ſelues, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe is from Grace.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Proſper.</hi> Euen after the fall there remained in <hi>Adam</hi> certaine ſeedes of Virtues, which by the Creators gift, are ſowen in the minde of euery man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item.</hi> That wee muſt beware leaſt wee ſo farre referre vnto God all the good workes of the Saints, that wee aſcribe nothing vnto mans nature, but onely that which is euill and peruerſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item:</hi> Therefore a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, findeth, entreth, becauſe vſing well the good of nature, by the helpe of this initiall grace, he hath obtained to come ſauing grace.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2011:12"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſecond Propoſition.</hi> Man, if not alwaies, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time preuenteth God by the preparation of his owne will. By which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour of nature, God is moued to bring, through the ayde of his Spirit, to the grace of Regeneration the Will ſo prepared.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Arminians.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARnoldus pag. 403.</hi> Man in the ſtate of Corruption, hath ſome reliques of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, to wit, ſome kinde of deſire of the good, which he knoweth.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arminius againſt Perkins, pag. 137.</hi> It is falſe, that an vnregenerate man is wholly fleſh, that is, that there is nothing in him but fleſh.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnoldus pag. 158.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius thinketh, that God in this manner will giue more and greater gifts to him that well vſeth grace. <hi>(That is, the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as before appeareth in the third Article of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius.)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>In the Epiſtle ad Walachros, pag. 45.</hi> Thoſe, who are
<pb facs="tcp:2011:12"/> amended by the naturall knowledge of the Law, and by the better vſe of common grace, are by God deemed ſomewhat worthy to receiue a further grace, and that by the gift and good pleaſure of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>5 Of the VVils freedome in conuerſion.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>OVt of Hilar. to Aug.</hi> They affirme the Will to be ſo free, that it can of it owne accord admit or refuſe cure or medicine.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Proſper.</hi> As for the Wills fredome, (they ſay) that life is layd hold on by thoſe, who beleeue of their owne accord, and entertaine the ayde of grace, by the merit, or act, of their credulitie.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> It is of the mercy of God, that men are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:
<pb facs="tcp:2011:12"/> but the following that call, is referred to their owne Will.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Petrus Diaconus contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum.</hi> They babble vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who ſay. To Will to beleeue is mine, or from me; but to helpe is of Gods grace. Whereas contrariwiſe, the Apoſtle teſtifieth, that the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing it ſelfe is giuen of God.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caſsianus.</hi> The whole is not ſo to be aſcribed to grace, but that free Will is to haue ſome ſhare of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe thereof.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item.</hi> Two things there are which worke mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Gods grace, and and mans obedience.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fauſtus lib.</hi> 1. Expounding Chriſts words, <hi>No man commeth to me, vnleſſe my Father draw him;</hi> ſayth, that to drawe is nothing elſe, but to preach, to ſtir vp with comforts of the Scripture, to deterre by reproofes, to propound things deſirable, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:2011:13"/> things dreadfull, to threaten iudgement, to promiſe reward.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARnoldus. pag. 337.</hi> Grace doth not ſo furniſh a man with new ſtrength, but that it alwayes remayneth in a mans power to make vſe of that ſtrength, or not.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hage Confer. pag. 282.</hi> A man may hinder his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, euen then, when God will regenerate him; or doth will to regenerate him.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnold. againſt Bogerman, pag. 263.</hi> All the operations, which God vſeth to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of man, being alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:2011:12"/> performed, yet this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion ſtill remaineth in mans power: ſo that hee can conuert, or not conuert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, beleeue, or not beleeue.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arminius againſt Perkins, pag. 223.</hi> The whole or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire cauſe, why this man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth, and that man belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not, is the will of God, and mans freewill.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arnold. againſt Tilen. pag. 136.</hi> It is not abſurde, that a man by his owne will ſhould diſcerne himſelfe from an vnbeleeuer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hage Conference, pag. 315.</hi> The diſcerning a man ſelfe from another man, may bee attributed vnto man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Grevinchove againſt Am. pag. 297.</hi> Nothing hinders, but that onely morall grace may make naturall men ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arminius againſt Perk. pag. 223.</hi> Faith is ſo from the meere will of God, that Gods will doth not vſe an omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent &amp; vnreſiſtable motion to beget faith, in men, but a gentle ſwaſion, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated for the mouing of
<pb facs="tcp:2011:13"/> mans will according to the nature of its freedome.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item, pag. 220.</hi> The Author of grace intendeth by grace to moue mans wil, to aſſent by a gentle and ſweete ſwaſion; which motion doth not onely not take away the free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of freewill, but alſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth it.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hage Confer. pag. 291.</hi> Is not that the moſt noble ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working vpon man, which is performed by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements and monition? Would not the working bee ſtrong enough, if it were ſuch as Satan vſeth?</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>6 Of Perſeuerance.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRopoſ.</hi> 3. For Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Faith and Grace, three needeth no new and ſpeciall grace. What we either haue by nature, or haue formerly goten by the ſpirit of grace, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb facs="tcp:2011:13"/> for ſuch Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2011:13"/>
                  <p>This Propoſition cannot be be fairely preſcribed for the true ſtate of the queſtion, much leſſe for the whole queſtion of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance. For the <hi>Demipelagians</hi> did not deny the ayde of new Grace for perſeuering, as is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by <hi>Proſpers</hi> words foreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:2011:13"/> God foreſaw, who would beleeue, and perſeuere in that Faith, which in proceſſe ſhould be helped by Grace.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Propoſition ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue beene thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Saint Auſtin in his Treatiſe of Perſeuerance.</hi> That Perſeuerance to the ende is in our power, and is not the gift of God.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Out of Hilar. to Auſt.</hi> Neither will they yeeld, that ſuch perſeuerance is giuen to any man, from which hee is not ſuffered to reuolt, but ſuch, as from which hee may by his Freewill fall away.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>HAge Confer. pag. 62. of the latter part.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance is ill called a gift. It is an act of the Will, which may admit, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the motion of the ſpirit.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Remonſtrants Theſes exhibited.</hi> All things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forelayd, which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and ſufficient for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, it remaines ſtill in the power of man to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere, or not perſeuere.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>7 The common clamorous Obiection.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Demipelag.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>PRroſper of the calling of the Gentiles.</hi> They obiect, that it is in vaine to labour to obtaine the worth and
<pb facs="tcp:2011:14"/> excellency of good works, in vaine to bee inſtant in Prayers, whereby God is intreated to grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, if ſo bee that the election vnto Chriſtian grace depend vpon the vnchangeable purpoſe of of God.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Proſper in his Epiſtle to Auſtin.</hi> They vpbraid, that all care of riſing out of ſinne is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from thoſe that are lapſed: that to holy men is miniſtred an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of lukewarmeneſſe; inaſmuch as the Elect can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall away by any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence, howſoeuer they behaue themſelues. That all induſtry is layed aſide, that vertues are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, if Gods determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preuent mans will.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Auſtin of Perſeuerance Chap.</hi> 12. The <hi>Pelagians</hi> obiect, That we tye Gods grace to Deſtiny. See alſo <hi>ad Bonifac. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Proſper. Ibidem.</hi> They ſay, that vnder the name of Praedeſtination, fatall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceceſsity is brought in.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Armin.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>HAge Conference, pag. 2 &amp;c. the latter part.</hi> This Doctrine in it ſelfe, and of it ſelfe, is an hinderance
<pb facs="tcp:2011:14"/> to godlineſſe, and alſo to good manners, both to the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and hearers. It leadeth to carnall ſecurity, it takes away true ſorrowe for ſinnes committed, as alſo the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full care of riſing vp from ſinne, and the feare of being hardned in ſinne in proceſſe of time.</item>
                     <item>It takes away Prayers, Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations, Obteſtations, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, Threatnings, Promiſes, Commands, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, Commendations, and Rewards.</item>
                     <item>This Doctrine bringeth into the Church <hi>Manichiſme, Stoiciſme, Libertiniſme, Epicuriſme.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>To the <hi>Arminians</hi> booke (of their <hi>Acta Synodalia</hi>) this Embleme is prefixed, An ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Lyon <hi>(the Armes of Holland)</hi> with a Capp <hi>(the badge of Liberty)</hi> ouer which is written this trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Motto.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>DESTINY DESTROYED, OR</hi> The ouerthrow of Fate.</q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2011:14"/>
                  <p>When <hi>Demipelagianiſme</hi> was obiected againſt <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius,</hi> he ingeniouſly anſwered,<note place="margin">Armin ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulo <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> that it <hi>might be a good</hi> Qaere, <hi>why</hi> Demipelagianiſme <hi>ſhould not be accompted true Chriſtianiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Proſper</hi> demonſtrating vpon ſubſtantial grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, that the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and <hi>Demipelagians</hi> ſticke together in the ſame myre, doth cage them both in the ſame <hi>Parallell,</hi> in theſe words.<note place="margin">Proſp cont. Collatorem Cap. <hi>41.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>The budds are of the ſame kinde, which come from the ſame ſeede, and that which is couched low in the roote, appeares in the fruit. We are not therefore to skirmiſh againſt theſe men with new leuied forces, nor to enter into a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall liſt, as againſt vnknown enemies. Theſe mens Engins were then ſhattered in pieces, then they fell to the ground in their Companions, and ringleaders of their pride, when</hi> Innocentius, <hi>of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, ſmote the heads of this abominable error with the dint of the Apoſtolicke Sword, when the Synod of the Biſhops of</hi> Paleſtina <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled</hi> Pelagius <hi>to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence againſt himſelfe, and his followers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If wee ty this miſhapen monſter with the bands of a Syllogiſme, <hi>Proteus</hi> being faſt manacled will vtter his concealed Oracle thus,</p>
                  <list type="syllogism">
                     <item>
                        <hi>Demipelagianiſme is true Chriſtianiſme</hi> (Arminius ſticks not at it)</item>
                     <item>But <hi>Demipelagianiſme is Pelagianiſme</hi> (Proſper avowes it)</item>
                     <item>Therefore <hi>Pelagianiſme is true Chriſtianiſme</hi> (though Catholike doctrine cry it downe.)</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>With which cloſe we ſumme vp this our</hi> Parallell.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2011:15"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
